Bearing?
方位
Mark.
目标
355.
方位 355
Range?
距离
Mark.
目标
MAN: 1000.
距离 1000码
Ready?
准备
Firing point, Captain.
发射准备
Fire 1!
发射一号
MAN: Number 1 running hot straight north.
一号向北直冲而去
Well, then we won't waste another one.
这样 我们就不用再浪费一个了
A solid hit, sir!
打得很准 船长
Want to confirm?
来确认一下
Nice shot, right down the middle.
打得漂亮 正中靶心
You want to take another look?
要不要再看一下
No.
不用
Surface for routine report and wreckage examination.
上升至海面 检查残骸做报告
Prepare to surface, look out to the conning tower.
准备上浮 观察哨上指挥舱
Well, Barney, that's another one for the book.
好吧 巴尼 又多了一项记录
Yeah.
是的
Great hit, captain.
打得好 船长
Nice shot, captain. Tankers hit them where they really hurt.
打得漂亮船长 击沉油轮对他们是致命伤
No word from comms up back yet, sir.
到现在还没有潜艇总部的消息 船长
I'll be in my cabin.
我会在我的房里
You'll have it, sir, if I get it.
随时向您汇报
I-- I mean, when I get it.
我的意思是如果收到消息的话
Pretty rough on the skipper.
船长很苦恼啊
Sure is. Has he heard anything about his family?
当然 有没有他家人的消息
Not a word since the Japanese invaded Manila.
自日本人入侵马尼拉后 就音信全无
(laughter)
(笑)
Let's light them up.
来 我们把蜡烛点上
Here we go.
好
One...
一
two...
二
Close your eyes and make a wish. There we are.
闭上眼睛 来许个愿 准备好
Close your eyes. All right, make a wish, darling.
闭上眼睛 对了 许个愿 亲爱的
Make a wish. Blow.
许个愿 吹
Ooh, she has done it.
哦 她做到了
Well, here we go.
来 开始吃了
One for each year, this is for you, darling.
给宝贝儿 一年一度的蛋糕
Barney.
巴尼
Well, it's her birthday, honey.
这是她的生日 亲爱的
Isn't it?
是不是
You don't mind, do you?
你不介意吧
Now some for everybody.
现在分给大家
Teresa, as soon as they finish,
泰瑞莎 等他们吃完后
take them inside and start opening the presents.
马上把他们带进去拆礼物
(music box playing)
(音乐盒播放)
Thank you, daddy.
谢谢 爸爸
You want to hold it?
你要抱一下吗
Well, it was a very nice party and we enjoyed being here.
很棒的派对 我们玩得很开心
Where do you think you're going?
你们这是要去哪儿
Well, we have to get back to the base.
我们必须得回基地去
What?
什么
Oh, no, you don't.
不 不会吧
You and Arch have sunk the whole enemy fleet
你和阿奇在这个月的演习中
five times this month in practice.
击沉整个敌方舰队五次
Six, honey, six!
六次 亲爱的 是六次
I wasn't counting doubleheaders.
我不算一天两次的记录
I just got word this morning
我今早刚接到报告
they've commissioned theShinaru.
日本人的 “士那若” 号 开始启用
Their newest carrier, is that straight dope, Barney?
是他们最新的航空母舰吗 巴尼
That's why I was late.
是 我为了这才迟到
You ought to leave them one carrier for the real war.
你应该给他们留一艘航母去参加真正的战争
Arch...
阿奇
you can bring me back a piece of theShinaruin this.
你可以用这个来捞“士那若”的碎片给我
This afternoon we're going fishing.
今天下午我们要去钓鱼
Well, if you say so.
好吧 听你的
Well, if we're going fishing let's get in the mood.
要是去钓鱼的话 得先培养点情绪
Fair enough.
有道理
Cheers.
干杯
Commander Doyle! Telephone!
道尔上校 电话
I'll get it.
我去接
Primo, I told you, no telephone calls
普里莫 我说过 道尔上校的电话
for Commander Doyle today.
今天一律不接
The naval base is very excited.
海军基地来的 非常紧急
They have to talk to Commander Doyle,
他们一定要跟道尔上校通话
something about Pearl Harbor.
是有关珍珠港的事
What was that about?
怎么回事
Oh, the base said it was important,
哦 基地说有很重要的事
something about Pearl Harbor.
有关珍珠港的
Jane, I want you to take Dede and get out of Manila
简 我要你带迪迪
just as quick as you can.
尽快离开马尼拉
Oh, Barney, now not that again.
哦 巴尼 你又来了
Manila is my home, I was born here and--
马尼拉是我的故乡 我生长在此
and now it's our home.
而它现在是我们的家
You know as well as I do what can happen here.
你和我一样明白 这里将会发生什么
You know what's coming now, don't you?
你很清楚知道接下来会发生什么 不是吗
Yes, I know.
是的 我知道
But if these islands are invaded, I'll take Teresa,
如果菲律宾群岛被日本人入侵 我会带着泰瑞莎
Primo, Dede, we'll go up in the hills
普里莫和迪迪 躲到山里去
and we'll be waiting for you there.
直到等你回来
Come on, darling, please let's not spoil her birthday.
拜托亲爱的 求你了 别破坏她的生日
All right.
好吧
I want to call the base first.
我得先跟基地联系一下
(imitating motor)
(模拟电动机)
(laughter)
(笑)
Nice big fat tanker, sir.
很肥胖的油轮 船长
Plenty of room on that, sir.
还可以加入更多记录
Throw that net away.
把那个网兜丢了
What do you mean throw it away?
什么意思 把它丢了
That's mine.
那是我的
Let's quit kidding ourselves, huh?
我们别再自欺欺人了
Manila was captured 10 months ago.
马尼拉在十个月前就被占领了
That doesn't prove that Jane was captured.
但这并不能证明简被抓了
Throw it away.
丢掉它
Barney, Jane knows what she's doing.
巴尼 简会照顾好自己的
She's probably hiding out in the hills somewhere.
她很可能藏在山里的某个地方了
As soon as she can get word to ComSubPac,
只要她能跟潜艇基地联系上
they'll let us know, believe me.
他们马上就会联络我们 相信我
I said throw it away!
我说了把它丢了
Yes, sir.
是 长官
I'm sorry.
我很抱歉
We're like a couple of kids yelling at each other.
我们就像两个小孩子似的 对着彼此叫嚷
Let me buy you some coffee, huh?
请你喝杯咖啡吧
Al, bring us some coffee, will you?
艾尔 来点咖啡
Aye aye, sir.
是 长官
He's too tense.
他太紧张了
Yeah.
是
Well, he wasn't too tense to get those.
但他的紧张并没有影响到他
Well, I'll ride with him.
我愿意做他的手下
That's big of you.
你真大方
Where would you get off?
如果你不愿意的话 你会在哪儿下船
I have a radar contact landmass bearing 256.
雷达侦察出 方位256度 有陆地
256?
256度
Got her.
找到了
Captain to the conning tower.
船长请到指挥舱
Land contact, sir.
看到陆地 长官
What's our position?
我们的位置在哪儿
Good old Fujiyama.
富士山
Well, we're home again, captain.
我们又回家了 船长
Yeah.
嗯
Land is one half miles off, sir, bearing 273,
我们距离海岸一英里半 方位273
we're in the mouth of Suruga Bay.
我们在骏河湾(日本最深的海湾)的入口
Well, you're a long way from England, lieutenant.
中尉 你离英国家乡可很远了
That's the advantage of ignorance, sir.
这就是无知的好处 先生
Lieutenant Redley, Royal Navy, assigned to Grayfish,
我是由英国皇家海军派遣到美国海军
for operational experience of new sonar equipment.
来学习最新的声纳运用技术
Well, it's our pleasure. We expect to show you something
那是我们的荣幸 将来要给你展示的东西
a lot more interesting than mountains.
可比那些山有意思得多了
You will, sir. We're overdue for some good clean fun,
你会的 长官 我们早就应该... 会有好机会的
you've earned it, sir.
你应得的
Left full rudder come to course 185.
左转185度 全速前进
Left full rudder, 185. Bensy!
左转185度 全速前进 Bensy
No surface contact, no aircraft contact.
海面没有船只和飞机
Down scope. Down scope.
降下潜望镜 降下潜望镜
Ready to surface, sir.
好了
Belay that. Now give me a sonar check.
很好 准备上升 再用声纳检测一下
Sound heads are rigged in, sir, sonar not operating.
声纳还未连接
There are no minefields indicated in this area, captain.
这地方没有水雷埋伏
Bring out the sound heads.
连接上声纳
Stand by to surface. Bring out the sound heads.
准备上升 连接声纳
The Japs could have a submarine here, Fisher.
也许日本人在这附近有潜水艇 费舍尔
That's right, I guess they could. I'm sorry, captain.
是 有可能 抱歉 船长
No contact on sonar, sir.
声纳没有反应
Surface. Surface, surface!
上升 上升 上升
Lookouts to the bridge. Aye, sir. Lookouts to the bridge.
观察哨上舰桥 是 长官 观察哨上舰桥
(siren blaring)
(警报声)
Break the hatch. Break the hatch.
打开舱门 打开舱门
Mr. Foley? Yes, sir?
福利 是
You are the officer of the deck, aren't you?
你今天是甲板值班吗
Yes, sir. Then you know that the OD
是 长官 那你应该知道 值班军官
is never the last one to the bridge.
不该是最后一个上甲板的人
Yes, sir.
是 长官
Object sighted, fishing sampan,
目测前方有帆船
10 degrees off port bow, sir.
距离船首左舷10度
It's probably a picket boat.
可能是艘巡逻船
Let him send back a report,
让它回去报告
maybe they'll send us out a target.
也许他们会派个大目标出来
Haven't you found it yet, Mr. Foley?
你还没有找到吗 福利
Yes, sir.
是 长官
Sorry about being late to the bridge, sir.
很抱歉 我上甲板迟了
Sorry is a word for funerals.
抱歉是个用在葬礼上的词
How late were you, Mr. Foley?
你到底迟到了多久 福利
About 10 seconds. Ten seconds?
大约十秒钟 十秒
Well, I'm sure that you realize a torpedo traveling
你应该知道鱼雷的时速是50英里
at 50 knots makes 1/7 of a mile in 10 seconds?
十秒之内就可到达1/7英里
Yes, sir. Won't happen again, sir.
是 长官 以后绝不会再发生了 长官
Say, cap, how about having some coffee?
船长 我们喝点咖啡吧
That's a good idea.
好主意
Now that you have the deck, Mr. Foley...
福利 现在由你负责甲板了
Yes, sir.
是 长官
Take care of it, huh?
好好干
Thank you, sir.
谢谢 长官
(knocking on door)
(敲门)
Great news, admiral.
好消息 将军
TheShinaru?
“士那若”号吗
No, sir, not a trace.
不 先生 连个影子都没有
Negative in five areas
五个地区都未发现
but others haven't called in yet, sir.
其他区还未报告 长官
What is your great news?
你有什么好消息
New list, sir. Confirmed by the Swedish legation
新的美国平民战俘名单
of American civilian prisoners of war.
由瑞典大使馆确认
Commander Adams, this is an operational office.
亚当上校 这里是作战指挥部
Sir, as of 2 weeks ago,
长官 在两个星期前
Barney Doyle's wife and baby are alive and well.
巴尼・道尔的太太和孩子都还活着 他们平安无事
Where?
在哪儿
The internment camp at Callabo. Are you sure?
在克拉博收容中心 你确定
The Swedish reports have been very reliable, sir.
瑞典人的报告一向非常可靠
Yes, they have.
对 没错
Crack it off to Barney as soon as you can raise him.
马上把消息通知给巴尼
Get it through and make it move.
一定要赶快联系上
Yes, sir.
是 长官
Adams!
亚当
Sir?
长官
Why are the enemy telling us this now?
为什么敌人要现在告诉我们
Well, the Swedes have been trying for weeks, sir.
瑞典人几周来一直在努力尝试 长官
You know how the enemy is.
你知道敌人是怎样的
That's it.
就是这个
Don't follow, sir.
我不明白 长官
When they tell us anything,
他们放出来的任何消息
it's because they want us to know.
就是想要 让我们知道
That's true, sir.
说得也是 长官
Why after all these months? Why now?
为什么在这么多个月之后 为什么要等到现在
I don't know, sir.
我不明白 长官
Neither do I.
我也不明白
Shall I hold this information, sir?
我应不应该压下这个消息
No, Barney has a right to know.
不 巴尼有权知道
Aye aye, sir.
是 长官
"Alive and well!"
安全无事
Who? Who? Who?
谁 是谁 是谁
What? Alive and well!
什么 安全无事
Who's alive and well?
谁安全无事
Captain's wife and baby!
船长的太太和孩子
(indistinct chattering)
(模糊地唠叨)太好了
Didn't I tell you?
我不是说过了吗
Now all we need is a piece of theShinaru!
现在只缺找到“士那若”号了
That Callabo is still an internment camp.
别忘了 那个克拉博收容中心 仍是个俘虏收容所
But it's the safest place in the war, Barney.
但那是眼下最安全的地方 巴尼
We hope.
希望如此
Well, you still want to get rest?
你还想请假吗
Rest? Now? Ha!
请假 现在 哈
What about that operational stuff?
作战指挥部有什么命令
We're alerted to stand by,
他们要我们准备好
surface for something urgent from ComSubPac.
随时应对紧急情况
Well, you heard him. Right.
你听到了 好
(knocking on door)
(敲门)
Adams, what's the matter with you?
亚当 你怎么了
Oh, I'm fine, sir.
哦 我很好 长官
Seen a ghost?
见到鬼了
TheShinaru, sir.
是“士那若”号 长官
Where? Where, show me.
在哪儿 指给我看
Right here, sir, headed northeast.
在这里 长官 它正往东北方向移动
We've had three good fixes and she outran them all,
我们三次准备好了攻击它 但都给它跑了
obviously headed for Tokyo Bay.
很明显它是开往东京湾
And Barney Doyle.
巴尼・道尔和他的
TheGreyfish is right there.
角鲨号潜艇就守在那儿
He's got her, Adams!
它跑不了 亚当
He'll get a shot at her, sir.
他会抓住机会发射鱼雷
Shot? He'll ram her if he has to.
用鱼雷 必要时他会撞沉它
Barney Doyle, if I could have picked my man.
巴尼・道尔是最好的人选
She's going right down his throat.
他会朝它直冲过去
This is going out to him, of course.
这是马上要发给他的吧
Sir, he's already got the operational data but--
长官 他已经收到作战通报了 但是...
But what?
但是什么
I think you ought to read the rest of that, sir.
我认为你应该全部看完 长官
Devils.
可恶
Those clever devils.
这帮狡猾的恶魔
I'm afraid this explains our great news, sir.
恐怕我们收到的那好消息就与此有关 长官
Too well.
大大有关
Barney got all of this yet? No, sir.
巴尼 收到这些消息了吗 没有 长官
He's just getting the operational stuff
我们刚刚才把有关“士那若”号的
on theShinarunow.
行动资料发给他而已
They think they've hit the jackpot.
他们以为中大奖了
Yeah.
哦
Message from Pearl.
珍珠港来的消息
The jackpot, sir.
大奖到了 长官
McKay! Aye, sir.
麦凯 是 长官
Relieve Mr. Foley on the bridge.
去甲板上换福利下来
Aye, sir.
是 长官
Give me the shortest course between here and Tokyo Bay.
我们要走捷径到东京湾
Tokyo Bay?
东京湾
Yes, sir!
是 长官
All ahead full. All ahead full, sir.
全速前进 全速前进 长官
All ahead full.
全速前进
(telephone ringing)
(电话铃)
Answer up, all ahead full, sir.
全速前进 长官
Mr. Foley! Yes, sir?
福利 是 长官
Run tests on the torpedo data computer
检测一下鱼雷发射装置
to make certain it's operating perfectly.
确保它运行良好
Recommended course 061, sir.
建议航向 061 长官
Very well.
很好
Down right to course 061.
右转 航向 061
061, sir.
航向 061
Mr. Milligan, send this message.
米利根 准备发报
Greyfishto ComSubPac.
角鲨致作战指挥部
Will do.
我们干
Captain to crew, upon reliable information
船长宣布 根据可靠情报
we are moving to intercept theShinaru.
我们准备拦截“士那若”号
The jackpot.
中大奖了
TheShinaru? That's right.
“士那若”号 没错
Hey, chief, what's all the excitement
嘿 头儿 大家干嘛对“士那若”号
about theShinaru?
那么大惊小怪
It's just another flattop.
它只是另一艘航母而已
Just another flattop? That's the number one target
另一艘航母 它是全美海军
of the whole United States Navy.
的头号攻击目标
It led the attack against us at Pearl Harbor.
就是它领头 率先攻击了我们的珍珠港
Well, that sets us up just great, Barney.
我们的位置非常好 巴尼
We've got plenty of depth there too.
海水也足够深
Captain, another message from ComSubPac.
船长 作战指挥部又发来个消息
Take it, Arch.
阿奇 看下这个
Yes, sir.
是
Checks out all right, sir.
一切正常 长官
Captain, theShinaru will undoubtedly
船长 “士那若”号一定
have a destroyer screen. Undoubtedly?
会有驱逐舰护航的 毫无疑问
Well, there might be chance to prang one of them, too.
也许有机会 我们可以打沉它一艘
Well, of course they're gonna be doing
那是当然 不过他们也会这么做
a little pranging of their own, lieutenant.
他们也会想尽办法打沉我们的 中尉
Yes, it won't be dull.
那时一定会很热闹
I'm sure of that.
一定会
Barney. Huh?
巴尼 唔
Read it to all hands.
念给大家听
This is the exec speaking for the captain.
这是副艇长替艇长广播
I'm gonna read you a message just received from ComSubPac.
念一段刚由作战指挥部发来的报告
Quote.
报告
"Information considered reliable here verified screen
据已证实的可靠情报
of two destroyers forShinaru
“士那若”号由两艘驱逐舰护卫
and in addition, repeat, in addition,
另外 重复
the transportYoshida Maru,
另有一艘运输船“吉田丸”号
which is being used to screen theShinaru."
也正被其一直征用
Go ahead.
继续念
"Further information considered equally reliable
据进一步的可靠消息
here is that the screening transportYoshida Maru
运输船“吉田丸”号上
is carrying all, repeat,
载有 重复
all, 1,400 American prisoners of war
总共载有1400名美国战俘
from camp Callabo to Japanese mainland."
从克拉博战俘收容所返回日本
End of quote.
报告结束
This is the captain.
我是船长
I will remind every man in this crew
我想要提醒各位
that we're trained to penetrate the enemy's
我们的任务 就是要穿透层层防护
protective screens and shields.
去击中目标
Barney, ComSubPac didn't say we have to attack.
巴尼 作战指挥部没要求我们非攻击不可
Why should they?
为什么需要说呢
That's what we're here for.
这就是我们来这儿的目的
Barney!
巴尼
Can I have a word with you?
我能和你私下谈谈吗
Notify the bridge I'm going below.
通知舰桥 我下去了
Bridge, captain going below.
舰桥 船长下去了
Well?
说吧
Barney, I came up through the hose pipe.
巴尼 我是穷苦出身
I've held every job in these boats,
我曾做过潜艇上的每项工作
enlisted man to officer, except skipper.
除船长外 经历过各项职位
You'd make a good one.
你将来会是个好船长
Well, this is something other people should say for me,
嗯 这是其他人该对我说的
but I can handle this boat right now.
可我现在就可以管理好这艘船
Well, you wouldn't be here if you couldn't.
如果你不行的话 你就不会在这儿
Barney, this attack is more than just routine.
巴尼 这次攻击作战非比寻常
Well, they all are.
每次不都这样
The message said all 1,400 prisoners.
这报告上说有1400名战俘
Your wife and baby are on that transport.
包括你的妻儿都在那运输船上
We are attacking theShinaru.
我们 会 攻击 “士那若”号
Barney, this is not an accident.
巴尼 这不是个意外巧合
Where do you think that transport will be
当你准备攻击的时候
when you have to shoot?
你以为那运输船会在哪儿
They're deliberately using her for a screen,
他们故意用那船来当保护网
and they've got two destroyers.
何况他们还有两艘驱逐舰
It'll be tough even getting close enough to shoot!
能够抵近攻击本就很困难
Don't you think I know that?
你以为我不知道吗
Barney, if we must shoot, let me do it.
巴尼 如果我们必须攻击 让我来做
That'll be all, Arch.
没别的事了 阿奇
That big one sure could be our flattop.
那艘最大的肯定就是我们的目标
The next big one, the transport,
第二大的就是运输船
that's the destroyer ahead, another one astern of the force.
一艘驱逐舰在前面 另一艘在后面
Range 9 miles.
距离有九英里
Bridge!
舰桥
Bridge, aye!
长官
Dive the boat!
下潜
Little bridge!
离开舰桥
Dive! Dive!
下潜 下潜
(honking twice)
(两次鸣笛)
Well, that was fast.
哦 (下潜速度)真快
Too fast.
太快了
Hustle and bustle, boy.
少嗦 小子
All ahead 2/3.
全速 2/3
All ahead 2/3, sir.
全速 2/3 长官
Cycle the vents.
关闭排气管
Cycle the vents!
All vents cycled and shut, sir!
所有排气管都已关闭
Battle stations torpedo.
鱼雷发射准备
(bell ringing)
(铃声)
Bearing, mark.
目标 方位
060.
方位 060
Range, mark.
目标 距离
6000.
距离 6000码
Angle in the ballast starboard 10.
船头右转十度
What about that transport?
那运输船怎么办
Same speed, same range.
同样速度 同样距离
Estimate 1,200 yards and starboard beam.
距离约1200码时 右舷发射
That's close, Barney, too close.
太近了 巴尼 太近了
TheShinaru'sindicated at doing 23 knots.
“士那若”号时速23海里
True bearing of the carrier is 294.
运行方位 294
We're 3 minutes from firing point if you plan on firing
如果你打算在距离1200码时开火
at 1,200 yards, sir.
那我们距离发射点只有三分钟 长官
Make it 1,000. Yes, sir.
改到一千码 是 长官
Destroyer is changing course.
驱逐舰正在改变航向
She's heading toward us.
它正朝我们来了
She's pinging on long scale
它正在长时间地侦测
but I don't think she's picked us up yet.
可我认为它还没发现我们
Give her time, old chap. It's hard work up there.
它工作还真辛苦 给它点时间
Rig for silent running.
静默运行
Steady as you go. Steady as you go, sir.
保持前进 保持前进
Make ready all forward tubes except for outer doors.
鱼雷发射管准备
Forward tubes are ready, sir, except for outer doors.
鱼雷发射管准备完毕
Very well. We'll try a spread of 6. Take the scope, Archie.
很好 我们试着分散攻击 升起潜望镜
Aye, sir.
是
Bearing, mark!
目标 方位
068.
方位 068
Range, mark!
目标 距离
1880!
距离 1880码
She's picked us up.
驱逐舰发现我们了
She's heading right down our throats.
它直冲我们而来
Set all torpedoes for 12 feet.
设定鱼雷在12丈畹奈恢
High speed, 2 degree spread.
高速前进 二度分叉
One minute to firing point, sir.
一分钟后可以发射
All tubes ready, sir, except for outer doors. Very well.
所有发射管准备就绪 很好
Destroyer approaching at high speed.
驱逐舰正在高速接近
Open outer doors. Open outer doors.
打开外门 (鱼雷发射管前盖) 打开外门
Up scope, this is a shooting observation.
升起潜望镜 便于观察发射
She's signaling.
它在发信号
Bearing, mark!
目标 方位
076.
方位 076
Range, mark!
目标 距离
1300!
距离 1300码
30 seconds to firing point, sir. On the bow?
30秒后发射 船头角度
10 degrees port, but we can't shoot,
左舷10度 我们不能发射
we'd hit theYoshida Maru. Confirmed, sir.
会打到运输船的 已确认 长官
A six-torpedo spread would hit the transport.
鱼雷分叉角度太大 会击中运输船
Chance for another setup?
有没有时间再作修正
Doubt it, chief. 20 seconds!
恐怕不行 二十秒
How many fish can you fire without hitting the transport?
能发射几枚鱼雷 而不击中运输船
Two, sir, possibly.
两枚 有可能
Barney, you can't.
巴尼 你不能这样做
I wouldn't risk it, sir. Nobody asked you to.
不要冒险 长官 没人问你
It's too close even for two fish.
离的太近了 连打两枚也不行
Destroyer approaching at high speed.
驱逐舰正在高速逼近
Bearing 042, range 1,500 yards.
方位 042 距离 1500码
Steady as you go.
保持前进
Steady as you go, sir.
Bow tubes stand by.
艇首鱼雷准备
Bow tubes are standing by, sir.
艇首鱼雷准备完毕
Barney, it's Jane and Dede.
巴尼 那是简和迪迪
10 seconds to shoot!
十秒钟后发射
You-- You can't.
你不能这么做
Firing point! Fire.
到达发射点 发射
Barney! Barney!
巴尼 巴尼
Number one running hot, straight and normal, sir.
一号发射正常
Number two running hot, straight and normal.
二号发射正常
That's a bit of all right.
他真是了不起
I hope so.
希望如此
Either way he is right.
不管怎样 他做得对
You want to take a look to confirm it, don't you, Barney?
巴尼 你不是想要确认一下结果吗
We better take her down deep, sir,
长官 我们最好下潜
the destroyer is almost on us.
驱逐舰已经快追上我们了
You've got to confirm, Barney.
你必须确认一下 巴尼
Close the outer doors.
关闭外门 (鱼雷发射管前盖)
关闭外门
Rig for depth charge. Rig for depth charge.
准备应战 准备应战
Down emergency, left full rudder.
紧急下潜 左满舵
Left full rudder. All ahead full.
左满舵 全速下潜
Answer up all ahead full!
我们正在全速下潜
How deep can you go? We've got 96 fathoms.
我们能潜多深 这儿有96海里深
Take her down to 300 feet. Take her down to 300 feet.
下潜300英尺 下潜300英尺
300 feet, aye, sir.
300英尺 是 长官
At least they're running straight.
至少鱼雷是直行前进的
What's the time on number one?
一号还有多久
Ten seconds to go, sir.
还有十秒
Rudder left full, sir.
左满舵 长官
Number one missed!
一号没有打中
(explosions)
(爆炸)
(indistinct chatter)
(模糊的颤音)船体中间进水
(模糊的颤音)船体中间进水 长官
How long to number two?
2号还有多久
8 seconds to hit theShinaru,sir.
八秒钟后击中“士那若”号
How many to-- How many to miss the transport?
要几秒 要几秒才打不中运输船
2 seconds, sir.
两秒
(explosion)
(爆炸)
It could have been a premature explosion, captain.
有可能会提前爆炸 船长
It could have been.
我是说也许
No, sir.
不会 长官
(explosions)
(爆炸)
I assume they've lost us for the moment, captain.
我认为他们暂时找不到我们
At 300 feet, sir.
300英尺深了 长官
Noise from the transport, sir.
有运输船的声音传来
She's breaking up.
船体开始破裂了
Water's rushing in.
海水正在大量涌入
Bulkheads are crushing.
船舱正在开裂
Reverse course.
调转航向
Reverse course. Right full rudder.
调转航向 右满舵
Bring her up to 60 feet.
上升到60英尺
60 feet, aye, sir!
60英尺 长官
The destroyers are waiting, captain.
那驱逐舰正在等我们 长官
I know that.
我知道
At 60 feet and holding, sir.
保持在60英尺 长官
What about that transport?
那运输船怎么样了
Those destroyers are waiting for us to pick up survivors.
那些驱逐舰正在等着我们上去援救生还者
They're using them as bait.
他们把生还者当诱饵
Well?
是吗
Let's get out of here.
我们离开这里
You take over, Arch.
你来负责 阿奇
Control room, 80 feet.
控制室 80英尺
80 feet, aye, sir.
80英尺 长官
5 degrees down.
缓慢下潜
Passing 095, sir.
越过 方位 095
Steady on 125.
保持 方位 125
125, aye, sir.
方位 125 长官
That's enough, thanks very much.
够了 非常感谢
Where's Arch?
阿奇在那儿
Telephone he said.
去打电话了
Yeah, he's been gone a half hour.
嗯 都去了半个钟头了
31 minutes.
31分钟
He's not coming back until I signal, I bribed him.
除非我打招呼 否则他不会回来 我贿赂了他
You what?
你什么
I bribed him. No, you didn't.
我贿赂了他 不会吧
No, you didn't do that, that's impossible.
哦 你不会这么做的 那不可能
You can't bribe Arch.
你不可能贿赂阿奇
You don't know what I offered.
你不知道我给了他什么
Barney, what's the word you use
巴尼 当一艘船保护另一艘船时
when one of your ships protects the other?
你管这叫什么
Ah, it's called screening. Oh, yes.
呃 叫护航舰 是的
You know, when you have one ship,
你知道 当你用一艘船
you want to protect another ship--
保护另一艘船时...
The principle is very clear.
原则很明确
Ship in front.
前面的船...
I'm tired of being screened, Barney.
我不想再被护航了 巴尼
For 5 months, you've kept Arch between us
五个月来 你一直让阿奇插在我们中间
like a chaperone, why?
就像个监护人 为什么
Because I love you, Jane, that's why.
因为我爱你 简 这就是原因
That's a good start, go on.
这是个很好的开端 说下去
I'm a bad risk.
我不是你理想的对象
Who's taking it? You or me?
那谁在冒险 你还是我
No.
不
Is it because there is going to be a war and we'll be in it?
是因为不久的将来 战争即将发生 而你我无法置身事外
Well, I've thought a lot about that too, Barney,
巴尼 在过去的5个月里
for the past 5 months.
关于这些我也想了很多
And if it all happens just exactly as you say it will,
如果一切都像你所说的那样发生了
I still want a duplicate of you.
我还是想要一个跟你一样的人
I kind of figured that I'd like to have a little girl first.
我有点想先要个小女孩儿
Well, fine then let's get the family started
哦好 那我们得先开始成立个家庭
before it's too late.
否则就太晚了
Are you sure?
你确信
Really sure that's what you want?
真的认为我们应该这样做吗
I've already promised Archie could be godfather.
我已经答应阿奇 让他做孩子的教父了
Exactly 34 minutes and 10 seconds.
整整34分十秒
And 5 months.
还有五个月
And all the rest of our lives.
还有我们余下的一生
(knocking on door)
(敲门)
Yes?
谁
Watch it, it's a little hot.
当心 有点烫
Thanks.
谢谢
Thanks, Arch.
谢谢 阿奇
Barney, can I say something?
巴尼 我能说几句吗
Yeah, yeah, what?
当然 说吧
I couldn't have done it.
是我的话我做不到
Well, you didn't have to.
你不需要做
Jane would have wanted you to try it.
简也会要你这么做的
Yeah.
是啊
Hey, come on.
嘿 来吧
Come on, sit down right here.
过来 坐这儿
Well, who-- Who has the deck?
谁在值班
Foley. Uh-huh.
福利 啊哼
Well, he's learning, that boy, huh?
那小子正在成长学习中
So am I.
我也是
I gave those two destroyers a slip
我躲开了那两艘驱逐舰
and reloaded and reported to ComSubPac.
重新装载了鱼雷并报告给作战指挥部
What did they say?
他们怎么说
Recommendation to return to Pearl Harbor at once.
建议立即返回珍珠港
What else? What else, sarge?
还有呢 还有什么 阿奇
Nothing else, just a routine sinking report.
没别的了 只是例行的沉船报告
I signed your name.
我签了你的名字
Thanks.
谢谢
Barney, let's head back to Pearl Harbor.
巴尼 我们回珍珠港吧
We still have 16 torpedoes left, haven't we?
我们还有16枚鱼雷 对吗
That's right.
没错
Well, they don't need them at Pearl.
珍珠港那边不需要这些
Battle stations torpedo.
鱼雷发射准备
(bell ringing)
(铃声)
Take a look at that setup.
来看一下
If they spot us on the shoals, we'll be in trouble.
要是他们在浅滩上发现我们 我们会有大麻烦
Let's head for deep water.
我们往深水去
Nope.
不
Are you going to attack?
你要进攻吗
Not that outfit.
不是这些船
Bearing? Mark!
目标 方位
350.
方位 350
Range? Mark!
目标 距离
1500.
距离 1500码
Make ready all bow tubes. Make ready all bow tubes.
所有鱼雷准备 所有鱼雷准备
Hang on the bow, starboard 30,
艇首预备 右舷30度
set torpedoes at high speed, depth 6 feet.
鱼雷设为高速 水深六英尺
It's gonna be a straight bow shot.
这将是一次艇首直接攻击
We're on the firing bearing now, sir.
已经到达发射点 长官
Range 1,000.
距离 1000码
Shoot.
开火
One fired, sir.
一号发射
Captain, what are we shooting at?
船长 我们在打什么
Net tender.
拉网船
Hmm?
唔
Their nets are still open.
他们的网还开着呢
Give me the time, Foley.
福利 报告时间
6 seconds!
六秒
(explosion)
(爆炸)
Solid hit.
正中目标
Come to course 045.
航向转为 045
Right full rudder, all ahead full.
右满舵 全速前进
045, right full rudder, all ahead full, aye, sir!
航向 045 右满舵 全速前进
(siren wailing)
(警笛嚎叫)
The destroyer's made a turn, captain.
驱逐舰转回来了船长
She found us yet?
它发现我们没
Through that?
杂音太大 它找不到
Makes an open room.
这就是漏洞
We're going through.
我们要穿插进去
Keep us in the clear.
保持警醒
Aye aye, sir.
是 长官
We're going into Tokyo Bay?
我们要进入东京湾吗？
Not going, sir, we are in.
不是进入 长官 我们已经到了
Tell them, Jojo.
周周 告诉船员
From captain to crew.
船长通报
We've entered Tokyo Bay.
我们已经进入东京湾
What if they find out that--
万一他们发现...
Shh.
嘘
First American sub in Tokyo Bay.
我们是第一艘进入东京湾的美国潜艇
How about dinner, Foley?
你觉得怎么样 福利
Great, if it's a round trip.
太棒了 希望是来回航程
(radar pinging)
(雷达脉冲)
Mines dead ahead.
正前方有水雷
Take us down fast!
紧急下潜
95 feet, left full rudder, come to course 005.
航向转为 005 左满舵 下潜95英尺
Left full rudder, 005, aye, sir.
航向转为 005 左满舵 下潜95英尺 长官
95 feet, aye, sir.
95英尺 长官
Rudder is left full, sir.
左满舵 长官
Contact to stern coming up fast, sir.
后面有船极速追来 长官
It's a destroyer pinging.
是艘驱逐舰
Steady as you go.
保持前进
Steady as you go, aye, sir.
保持前进 长官
Don't any of you chaps find it a trifle warm?
各位是不是觉得身上有点发热
Do you want to go sightseeing, sir?
你干嘛 难道想要去观光吗 长官
It seemed a good idea then.
听着像是个好主意
All ahead dead slow.
慢速前进
All ahead dead slow, sir.
慢速前进 长官
The tin can is closing fast, 700 yards, sir.
驱逐舰快追上我们了 距离700码 长官
He's following us into the minefields.
它跟着我们进入了布雷区
He is a fool coming in here.
它跟过来实在太愚蠢了
You could say he has guts too, sir.
也可以说它很有胆量 长官
Well, he won't have them long.
很快就没有了
(explosion)
(爆炸)
He's a happy warrior.
它是个无畏的勇士
Left standard rudder.
转舵向左
Left standard rudder, aye, sir.
转舵向左 长官
Better get back into the channel.
我们最好返回海湾通道
If we can make the channel, we'd have 150 feet
要想返回海湾通道
of good water, captain.
我们必须潜深150英尺 船长
(metal clanging)
(金属叮当声)
Sounds like we fouled a mine cable up forward.
听着像是船头被水雷的线缆钩住了
All stop, all back emergency, rudder amidships.
停车 紧急倒退 转舵回中
All stop, all back emergency, rudder amidships, aye, sir.
停车 紧急倒退 转舵回中 长官
All stop.
停车
All ahead dead slow.
慢速前进
Come to course 335.
航向转为 335.
335, aye, sir!
335 长官
Beautiful, sir.
干的漂亮 长官
I wouldn't have missed that.
真令我大开眼界
I would.
我可不想
How do you feel, Benson?
你觉得怎样 本森
I haven't felt for an hour, sir.
我好长时间都没知觉了 长官
There's a faint sound, sir.
听到个很微弱的声音 长官
Nothing close anyway.
反正不太靠近我们
We got room to turn seaward now, captain.
我们有足够空间转向进入海湾通道了 船长
Steady as you go. Steady as you go, aye, sir.
保持前进 保持前进 长官
Bring us up to 62 feet.
上升到62英尺
62 feet, aye, sir!
62英尺 长官
Going through.
借过
But if they close the nets behind us?
万一他们把我们身后的网关上
Oh, that's all that sound is, sir.
噢 就是这个声音
All?
噢
But...
但是...
if the nets are closed...
如果网关上了
Tokyo is a big town, sir.
东京是个大城市
We'll find a boarding house.
我们会找到公寓住的
At periscope depth, captain.
可以升起潜望镜了 船长
Any contacts with stern?
后面还有没有声音
No contact, sir.
没有 长官
Take it up.
上升
Straight out ahead, minefield to port.
前方无障碍 水雷区在左
Mark it on the chart, Mr. Fisher,
在航海图上做好标记 福利
for the round trip.
便于我们往返进出
Marking it now, sir.
正在标记
You got her, huh?
你找到它了 呵
Look.
你看看
TheShinaru,gentlemen.
各位 “士那若”号
Battle stations torpedo, make ready all bow tubes.
做好战斗准备 鱼雷发射管待命
(bell ringing)
(铃声)
All tubes ready, sir.
鱼雷发射管 准备完毕
Bearing, mark.
目标 方位
338.
方位 338
Range, mark.
目标 距离
1500.
距离 1500码
Destroyer cutting in.
驱逐舰来了
Range will be perfect in 8 seconds.
再过八秒到达发射点
We haven't got 8 seconds.
我们没有八秒钟
Commence firing.
命令发射
Fire!
发射
All six fired, sir. Take her down fast.
六枚全部发射完毕 长官
Take her down fast! Left full rudder.
急速下潜 左满舵
Left full rudder, aye, sir.
急速下潜 左满舵 长官
The destroyer is intercepting our torpedoes, captain!
驱逐舰挡住了我们的鱼雷 船长
(siren wailing)
(警笛嚎叫)
Missed.
没打中 (没打中“士那若”)
We missed.
我们没打中
Rotten luck.
真不走运
Contact, here we go again.
敌舰 又追来了
(explosions)
(爆炸)
The upper hatch is sprung!
顶舱出现破裂
See if you can dock it down!
看能不能堵住它
(groans)
(呻吟)
Get him up on the bunk.
把他抬床上去
Pharmacist's mate to forward torpedo room.
叫医务官到鱼雷舱来
Ease your bubble to zero!
老天 威力真强
Buckeye, check for damage!
巴凯 检查损坏程度
All compartments, report in!
各舱室报告情况
Wait a minute!
等一下
Forward torpedo room to conning tower,
艇首鱼雷舱报告指挥台
we have one man knocked out and are taking water
舱内进水 可以控制
but we'll handle it.
有一人晕倒
You check on the damage.
你去检查一下损坏情况
Hallert, get 50 pounds of pressure in there,
哈勒 再增加压力50磅
reload those tubes fast and clear the room
尽快重新装上鱼雷 除了你和那昏倒的
except for yourself and one man.
其他人马上离开鱼雷舱
(explosions)
(爆炸)
Flooding under control, Barney.
进水已被控制 巴尼
Pressure in the room is holding, tubes are reloaded,
压力已经达标 鱼雷也装上了
Hallert and one man standing by.
留两人值守
Destroyer is all over us, captain.
驱逐舰已遍布我们四周 船长
I'm all right.
我没事
How close are we to the minefield?
我们离水雷区有多远
Estimate 600 yards starboard, sir.
距右舷600码远 长官
Well, run down the Bay,
我们沿着海湾
keep us close to that minefield as possible.
尽量靠近水雷区航行
Aye, sir.
是 长官
That destroyer is laying back, sir.
驱逐舰正在撤退
Maybe doesn't want to see his ancestors.
也许他们不想重蹈覆辙
Captain, may I say something?
船长 我能不能说两句
Well, if there's time.
行 反正有时间
In the Skagerak one night
我们在北欧海域作战时
Germany boats chased us into a minefield
有次德军舰艇把我们驱赶入水雷区
and we made them think they'd killed us
我们引爆了其中一枚水雷
by exploding one of their own mines.
让他们以为把我们炸沉了
With what, good wishes?
怎么引爆 难道祈祷吗
Not that we were saving those.
不 我们使用了艇尾鱼雷
We used our stern tubes, sir.
最后我们成功脱险
Stern tubes stand by.
艇尾鱼雷准备
Stern tubes ready, sir.
艇尾鱼雷准备完毕 长官
Set gyro at 90 degrees.
陀螺仪设为90度
Gyro set at 90 degrees, sir.
陀螺仪已设为90度 长官
Fire all four.
发射四枚
All four fired, sir.
四枚全部发射
(explosion)
(爆炸)
All stop. All stop.
停车
All stop, aye, sir!
是 停车
Goldy?
戈尔迪
The destroyer is turning away, sir.
驱逐舰正在掉头撤离
He is heading back up the bay.
它要回东京湾去了
The sound is fading.
声音正在逐渐减弱
I think we're okay.
我想我们没事了
By golly, it worked.
天那 我们成功了
Hey, Redley.
嘿 雷德利
I thought you came here to learn from us.
我以为你是来向我们学习的
I have, sir.
我学到了
But I'm expected to take the information back.
不过 我很期待能把学到的东西带回去
Well, Fuzz, we made it.
嘿 福奇 我们逃出来了
Yeah.
是
To the nets.
只到阻拦网而已
Forward torpedo room.
艇首鱼雷准备
Open outer doors.
打开外门 (鱼雷发射管前盖)
Forward torpedo room, open outer doors.
艇首鱼雷准备 打开外门
Nets 700 yards ahead, sir.
阻拦网在前方700码 长官
Fire all bow torpedoes, no spacing.
艇首鱼雷全部发射 没有间隔
(explosion)
(爆炸)
Close outer doors.
关闭外门
All ahead standard.
全速前进
All ahead standard, aye, sir!
全速前进 长官
We're in the clear.
我们出来了
Well, thanks.
谢谢
Thanks for all of us.
我们全体都感谢你
Thank you, sir.
谢谢 长官
Recommend course 185, captain.
建议航线 185 船长
Very well.
很好
Come to course 185.
航向 185
185, aye, sir.
航向 185 长官
Secure from battle stations, repair battle damage.
修复各舱损坏部位
Secure all battle stations, repair all battle damage.
Keep me informed, Arch.
阿奇 随时报告情况
Aye, sir.
是 长官
(music box playing)
(音乐盒播放)
JANE:Oh, what did you  say to daddy, Dede?
哦 迪迪 你想跟爸爸说什么
DEDE:Thank you, daddy.
谢谢 爸爸
You want to hold it?
你要抱一下吗
JANE:Yes, I know.
是 我知道
But if these islands  are invaded,
如果菲律宾群岛被日本人入侵
I'll take Teresa,  Primo and Dede,
我会带着泰瑞莎 普里莫和迪迪
we'll go up in the hills  and we'll be waiting  for you there.
躲到山里去 直到等你回来
Come on, darling, please  let's not spoil her birthday.
拜托亲爱的 求你了 别破坏她的生日
He's still asleep, Al.
他还在睡觉 艾尔
Yes, sir, I know, sir, but he ain't had a bite.
我知道长官 可他一直没吃东西
He'll eat when he wakes up!
他醒了会吃的
I'm sorry, Al, sleep is what he needs.
我很抱歉 艾尔 他需要的是睡眠
Yes, sir.
是 长官
I just looked in on him, Jennings.
我刚去看过他 杰宁
He's still asleep, don't bother him.
他还在睡觉 别打扰他
Call it what you want, sir, we could help him.
随你怎么说 长官 可我们或许能帮他
Wouldn't you just postpone what he's going through?
你能帮他减轻 他目前所受的痛苦吗
Probably.
也许能
Then let him alone, will you?
那就让他独自清静会儿 好吗
You better take it easy yourself, sir.
你自己也该放轻松点 长官
Nothing wrong with me, I'm fine.
我没事的 我很好
Well, what do you want me to do?
好吧 你要我怎么做
Well, right now why don't you go topside for a smoke?
您现在最好上去抽根烟
Ah, maybe you're right.
也许你是对的
Okay.
好吧
But leave him alone, huh?
别去打扰他 阿
Thanks.
谢谢
Why did she love you so much?
她为什么那么爱你
I don't know, I guess it was my personality.
我不知道 大概是我的个性吧
What's the matter? The other guy had more personality?
怎么啦 还有另外一个人个性更好吗
No, all he had was a car.
不 他只有辆车
So why didn't you get a car? Yeah, why didn't you get a car?
那你干嘛不买辆车 是啊 你干嘛不买辆车
And drive around all that traffic?
还得应付交通
(laughing)
(笑)
Hey, I think he's right.
嘿 我想他说的对
Hey, knock it off, you guys.
嗨 别闹了 伙计们
How's the captain, sir? He's coming along fine.
船长怎么样了 长官 他很好 没事了
Oh, that's good. Good.
哦 太好了 好
Mr. Sloan, have you ever had any trouble with dames?
呃 斯隆先生 你跟女人遇到过麻烦吗
Well, yeah. Once in a while.
哦 是 偶尔也有过
(laughter)
(笑)
Good morning, gentlemen.
早上好 先生们
Morning, sir. Morning, sir.
早安 长官 早安 长官
Good morning, sir.
早安 长官
Why don't you boys get some coffee?
你们为什么不去喝点咖啡
I'll take over the watch.
这里我来值守
Yes, sir.
是 长官
Aye, sir.
What's our position?
我们位置在那儿
8 days, 16 hours and...
我们距离皇家夏威夷酒店
10 minutes from the bar of the Royal Hawaiian.
还有八天十六小时零十分钟
I was out that long?
我昏睡了这么久吗
Why shouldn't you sleep?
干嘛不睡
Yeah.
是啊
We're going home.
我们要回家了
What did you report?
你怎么报告的
I told ComSubPac to have the Royal Hawaiian
我告诉作战指挥部 交代皇家
put out another bartender.
夏威夷酒店 多安排个酒保
What else did you tell them?
还说什么了
Nothing else.
没有了
Arch, you know that...
阿奇 你知道的
sleep as you call it,
你心里很清楚
that could put me behind a desk
你所称之为的“睡眠”
for the rest of the war.
是有可能让我失去船长资格的
You know that, don't you?
不是吗
Everybody sleeps.
大家都需要睡觉的
Who knows how long you slept?
谁知道你睡了多久
You do.
你知道
If ComSubPac should ask you anything, what would you tell them?
如果作战指挥部 追问这些事情 你会怎么说
Why should they ask? What would you tell them?
他们干嘛要问 你会怎么回答
If they ask, Barney, I'd have to tell the truth.
如果他们问了 巴尼 我一定会说实话
Arch, you are the only man alive
阿奇 你是唯一一个活着
who can keep me from getting theShinaru.
能阻止我击沉“士那若”号的人
Don't you think I want it too, Barney?
你不觉得我也很想击沉它吗 巴尼
Thanks.
谢谢
When he gets here, let's really pour it on him.
当他过来的时候 我们捉弄他一下
Yeah.
好
(humming) Here's your hat.
这是你的帽子
You're looking for me, Benson?
本森 你找我吗
You were the last one to look at the slides yesterday?
昨晚最后一个看幻灯片的人是你 对吗
Yeah, and they were the greatest--
是啊 而且片子非常棒
Look, don't try to worm out of it.
听着 别想找什么借口
You know what you did? You touched it.
你知道你做了什么 你摸了它
Touched it? And smudged it!
摸了它 而且还弄脏了
Smudged it? Left your big fat fingerprint all over it.
弄脏了 而且还把你的大肥手指印 都印在上面了
Look at that!
你看看
Where?
在那儿
You know where. You mean right by--
你知道在哪儿 你是说 靠近...
No, down in the right hand corner.
不 就在右下角这儿
Oh, yeah, I think I see it.
哦 对 我好像看见了
You think you see it? Of course you see it!
你好像看见了 你当然看得见
First time I let some jughead handle the slides,
我第一次让个笨蛋来处理幻灯片
he ruins my business. Metcalf, put this down.
他就毁了我的生意 梅特卡夫 把这记下
Garrity, no slides for 2 weeks!
盖瑞迪 两周之内不准看幻灯片
No slides for 2 weeks?
两个星期 没幻灯片看
Hey, Benson, wait a minute, I want to talk to you.
嘿 本森 等一下 我要跟你谈一谈
Permission to come aboard, sir.
请准许上船
Certainly, sir.
准许 长官
Barney. Admiral.
巴尼 将军
Hello, Adams. Hello, Barney, how are you?
你好 亚当 你好 巴尼 身体好吗
Nice to see you.
很高兴见到你
Any further news, sir?
有进一步的消息吗 先生
Sorry, Barney, no, not a word.
抱歉 巴尼 毫无音讯
No survivors were picked up, huh? No report of it.
没有生还者被救上来吗 没有跟这有关的报告
They've put a blackout over the whole thing.
他们完全封锁了消息
You know as much as we do.
你知道的跟我们一样多
How soon can I get back, sir?
我要多久才能回船上去 长官
Barney, submarines work better without holes in them.
巴尼 潜艇在没有破损的情况下 会运行得更好
Well, these aren't too bad, admiral,
嗯 情况不是太严重 将军
if I can have first priority in dry dock.
如果您能优先安排替我们修理
Well, we'll do our best.
嗯 我们会尽力而为的
Meanwhile, your orders are take it easy.
你现在的命令是多多休息
We have rooms for you
我们在皇家夏威夷酒店
at the Royal Hawaiian, commander.
替你准备了房间 指挥官
That's fine. Thank you.
那太好了 谢谢
Are you joining me for luncheon, commander?
跟我一起共进午餐好吗 指挥官
Thank you, sir.
谢谢 长官
What's the matter? Can't you sleep?
怎么了 你睡不着吗
Are you kidding?
开什么玩笑
You're keeping me awake.
你吵得我无法入睡
Look, Barney, you won't sink theShinaruin here.
我说 巴尼 你不会在这儿击沉“士那若”的
That admiral has given us the run around.
你心里很明白 将军在跟我们兜圈子
You know that, don't you?
他在敷衍我们 不是吗
He gave us first priority in dry dock.
他给我们的船 优先维修的待遇
That's right, that...
说的没错
That he did.
他是这么做了
He didn't ask you anything else, did he?
可他没再问你其他的事 对吗
Huh?
阿
For the last time, no.
最后一次回答你 没有
Are you sure?
你确定
Now will you get to bed and get some rest?
你现在还是回床上休息去吧
Okay.
好吧
Okay, buddy, okay.
好吧 哥们儿 好吧
Lieutenant Sloan reporting, sir.
斯隆(海军)上尉报告 长官
Good morning, Arch. You sent for me?
早上好 阿奇 您找我吗
Sit down.
坐下
Thank you, sir.
谢谢 长官
Arch, what would be the best possible news
阿奇 我能给你的
I could give you?
最好消息是什么
Sailing order, sir.
角鲨号修复
Greyfishis ready.
可以起航的命令 长官
That is news.
那不算是最好的消息
It'll do very nicely, sir.
可我已经很满意了 长官
How would you like your own boat,
你想不想要一艘自己的船
Lieutenant Commander Sloan?
指挥官 斯隆上尉
My own command?
我自己的船
Your promotion has just come through.
你的升职命令刚刚下达
That's a long haul from apprentice seaman, Arch.
阿奇 你从最底层做起直到现在 这是段漫长而又艰苦的历程
A brand new sub waiting at New London
现在 一艘崭新的潜艇正在新伦敦(地名 在美国)
for a top skipper.
等待它的首任船长
The record says that's you.
那 就是你
Funny, I-- I don't know what to say.
有意思 我-我都不知道该说什么了
Every skipper you've served with has said it for you.
每一位和你共事过的船长 都说你堪当此任
Well, thank you, sir.
谢谢 长官
May I ask a question, sir?
我能问个问题吗 长官
All you like.
尽管问
Is Barney taking theGreyfishout again?
巴尼会不会再回角鲨号当船长
Arch, that's a different problem. Not to me, sir.
阿奇 这是另外一个问题了 对我不是 长官
You've earned the command, Arch.
你该有自己的船了 阿奇
And Barney has earned another crack at theShinaru,sir.
而巴尼也该有另一次机会去打沉“士那若”号
He's overdue for a desk job and a good rest.
他早应该去转做行政工作 再好好休息一下了
He's still the best skipper you've got, admiral.
他仍是你手下最好的船长 将军
There's more than one factor in duty assignments, Arch.
分配工作时要考虑很多因素和条件 阿奇
You've got them all for your own boat.
这些条件你都具备 所以你该有艘自己的船
I'd still have the same as Barney's exec, sir.
我仍想继续当巴尼的副手 长官
If you want to remain his exec.
我条件不变 你还是想继续当他的副手
I do, sir.
是的 长官
Arch, are you covering for him?
阿奇 你是不是在替他掩饰
Covering what, sir?
掩饰什么 长官
Was he knocked out after you came out of Tokyo Bay?
他是否在你们撤出东京湾后就一直昏睡
3 days, sir.
三天 长官
But you know what he'd been though.
可你也知道他都经历了些什么
Of course I do.
我当然知道
But only you know what came out of it.
但只有你一个人知道到底发生了些什么
Well, he's passed his new physical exam.
他新的体格检查通过了
Perfect, the problem is not physical.
很好 他现在的问题不是身体上
Is he fit, Arch?
他到底还行不行 阿奇
He's tense, of course, but...
他当然有点紧张 但是...
I'd be worried if he weren't.
如果他不紧张 我才担心
I think he's fit
我想他还是行的
and I want to sail with him.
我想跟他一起出航
TheShinaru is still unreported.
“士那若”号至今仍毫无消息
The best I could give him would be a long shot hunch.
我能给他最好的 就是一个希望极其渺茫的猜想
I'd like to try it, sir.
我很想跟巴尼一起
With Barney.
再去试试 长官
Thanks, Arch, you've helped me.
谢谢 阿奇 你帮了我不少
Thank you, sir.
谢谢 长官
But what about Barney?
那巴尼呢
You've helped him, too, to one more trip.
你也帮他争取到了再一次出航的机会
Get thatShinaruthis time or you'll have to kill her
这次要是再打不沉“士那若”号
with your own boat.
就得用你自己的船去打了
Yes, sir.
是 长官
Admiral, you know Barney.
将军 你了解巴尼
If he knew I'd been offered my own command,
如果他知道我获得了晋升的命令
he'd make me take it.
他会逼我接受的
Yes, he would.
没错 他会
All right, I won't tell him, because after this trip,
好吧 我不会告诉他的 因为在这次出航之后
I'm making you take it.
我会逼你接受的
Yes, sir.
是 长官
What's wrong?
怎么了
Kiska... approach patrol.
要我们巡逻吉斯卡岛
You know what that means, don't you?
你知道这意味着什么 不是吗
Well, they put us right, right in the deep freeze.
他们把我们打入了冷宫
Easy, Barney.
放松 巴尼
After all he isn't running the war just for one boat.
毕竟他不能只为了一艘船而开战
You reading his mind now?
你现在能明白他的意思吗
Well, no, I talked to him.
不能 不过我跟他谈过
What?
什么
Barney, theShinaru is unreported.
巴尼 那“士那若”号没有一点消息
He said he's giving us the best long shot hunch he has,
将军说 他会给我们他认为的最佳猜想地点
and his hunches are based on good intelligence.
而他的猜想都是基于良好的情报来源
What else did you talk about?
你们还谈了些什么
You.
你
Go on.
说下去
He wanted to know how long you'd been knocked out
他想知道自东京湾撤离后
after Tokyo Bay.
你昏睡了有多久？
I told him.
我告诉他了
What else did you tell him, hmm?
你还告诉他些什么 嗯
I told him I wanted to sail with you.
我说我要跟你一起出航
You go shoot your mouth off to the admiral
你去跟海军上将胡说八道
and next thing you know we're headed for Kiska.
然后接下来你瞧 我们去守吉斯卡岛了
Steady, boy.
我在支持你
You could have quit me, you could have asked
你本可以要求调职的
for a transfer, why didn't you?
你可以离开我的 为什么不
Yes, I could have quit you!
是的 我本就可以离开你的
Well, why didn't you?
那你为什么不那样做
Don't you know that yet?
你难道不明白吗
Just a minute, Mr. Sloan.
等一下 斯隆先生
Now you get this straight.
你现在给我听清楚
I...
我...
I'm gonna get theShinaru in spite of what you think,
我一定要打沉“士那若”号 不管你怎么想
in spite of what the admiral thinks,
不管海军上将怎么想
in spite of what anybody thinks.
不管其他任何人怎么想
Now you got that straight?
听清楚了吗
Yes, sir.
是 长官
I got it.
我清楚了
That's all.
就这样
Captain!
船长
Captain! Yes.
船长 什么事
TheShinaru,she is heading for Kiska Harbor.
是“士那若”号 它正开往吉斯卡港
Give me the shortest course
给我找出从这儿
between here and Kiska Harbor.
到吉斯卡港的最短航线
Aye aye, sir.
是 长官
Recommended base course 085, Captain.
建议主航向为 085 船长
Come to course 085!
调整航向为 085
All ahead full.
全速前进
085, aye, sir.
航向 085 长官
All ahead full.
全速前进
All ahead full, sir.
全速前进 长官
Message to  Bluefin:
给蓝鳍金枪鱼号发消息
Follow us, base course 085.
跟随我们 主航向 085
Aye, sir.
是 长官
Answer up, all ahead full, sir.
全速前进 长官
Mr. Sloan, come to the bridge.
斯隆先生到舰桥来一下
What does this mean?
这个是什么意思
About bringing you back for your own boat?
为了你自己的船才把你叫回来
What does it sound like?
你听着像什么意思
When did the admiral offer you your own command?
将军什么时候给你机会开自己的船
Why should you care?
你关心这干嘛
I wish you'd taken it, Arch.
阿奇 我真希望你接受了
That makes two of us.
我也是
I want to follow in your footsteps, Barney...
我想要一直追随你的 巴尼
but one of us has changed.
但我们中有一个人变了
We're here, sir, part of the entrance to Kiska Harbor.
长官 我们已经到了吉斯卡港的入口
Radar?
雷达
There's the headland, sir.
那里是海岬 长官
TheBluefin, 500 yards astern of us.
蓝鳍金枪鱼号在我们后面500码
No more going on the surface.
我们从海面上进入港口
Clear the bridge.
清理舰桥
TOGETHER: Clear the bridge!
You men, go down and get yourselves
伙计们下去喝点咖啡
some coffee and get warm real fast.
让身子尽快暖和起来
Foley? Yes, sir.
福利 是 长官
Foley, stand by the TDC.
福利 你守在TDC(鱼雷数据计算机)边上
Yes, sir. How about the hatch?
是 长官 那舱门口怎么办
Lock it down! Lock it down!
关闭舱门 关闭舱门
We're attacking, of course. We are.
我们要准备进攻了 是啊
I'd dive the boat, sir.
我来把船潜下去 长官
I'm aware that we have no visibility,
我知道我们目前没有能见度
that's why I want my radar to help my sonar.
所以我要利用雷达配合声纳来查看
Radar is already icing,
雷达已经结冰了
and this is a tricky entrance, sir.
而这港口不易进入
Left full rudder, come to course 225.
左满舵 调整航向 225
All ahead 2/3.
全速2/3
Left full rudder, 225.
左满舵 航向 225
All ahead 2/3, aye, sir!
全速2/3 长官
Contact. Broad contact.
声纳有反应 有巨大反应
This is all across both bars. Radar?
我们要越过一道屏障 雷达
No contact to head, sir.
没有反应 长官
My antenna must be iced.
肯定是天线冻住了
All I'm getting is a faint headland.
我得到的都是微弱信号
Got it now!
找到了
Look at all those blips.
看 那么多亮点
Half the Jap navy must be in there.
半数的日本海军(舰艇)都在里面
I count nine ships, sir.
我数了下有九艘船
Range? 3,000 yards.
目标距离 3000码
That big blip must be the flattop.
那最大的亮点一定是艘航母
It's not the same contact, sir.
这跟刚才那个不是相同的反应
No, sir, mine's a broad contact 200 yards ahead.
是的 长官 另一个大反应距离我们前方200码远
It could be the log and chain boom
这可能就是情报部门所说的
imported by intelligence, captain.
由进口原木和链式吊杆构成的巨大屏障
How close? Coming fast, sir.
有多近 就快到了
We'll stay for one more confirmation.
再做一次确认
It's a bad risk, captain.
太危险了 船长
It's parked at 1,200 yards, just coming around the headland tip.
那航母就停在海岬尖角附近 距离我们1200码
She's attacking, sir.
它正在攻击我们 长官
(explosions)
(爆炸)
Hard boom dead ahead, sir.
巨大障碍就在我们正前方 长官
Dive! Yes, sir.
下潜 是 长官
Dive the boat.
紧急下潜
(explosions)
(爆炸)
(alarm blaring)
(警报响起)
Come on! Come on right away!
快点 马上过来
(alarm blaring continuously)
(警报持续鸣响)
Mr. Buckeye reports pressure building up in the boat, sir.
长官 巴克艾报告艇上的压力正越来越大
How much pressure? How much pressure?
压力多少 压力多少
Eight pounds, sir. We got a ruptured air line but we can handle it!
八磅 长官 我们有条空气管破裂了 不过可以修好
How much depth do we have here?
这里有多深
30 fathoms, sir.
30英寻(约55米) 长官
Take us down to 90 feet.
下潜至90英尺
Take it down to 90 feet.
下潜到90英尺
90 feet!
90英尺
We've lost both scopes, sir.
两个潜望镜都卡住了 长官
Radar inoperative, sir.
雷达失灵 长官
Antenna must have been carried away.
天线一定是被撞毁了
Steady as you go. Steady as you go, sir.
保持原航向 保持原航向 长官
All compartments report in.
各舱室报告情况
What's the matter, Barney?
怎么了 巴尼
Pharmacist, right to the conning tower on the double.
医务官 立即马上跑步到指挥舱来
Pharmacist right on the double, aye, sir!
医务官立即马上跑步赶到 长官
Come sit over by the chart table, Barney.
过来坐到海图桌边上 巴尼
Bluefinis calling in for a check, sir.
长官 蓝鳍金枪鱼号呼叫 要求确认目前情况
Tell them we're proceeding with the attack.
告诉他们 我们正在继续攻击
Aye, sir.
是 长官
90 feet and holding, sir!
保持在90英尺深 长官
Get his arm on the table.
把他的手臂放到桌上
Take a look at this.
检查一下
How is it?
怎么样
It's broken above the elbow, captain.
肘部上方骨折了 船长
I can handle it.
我可以把它接上
Go ahead then.
那就做吧
Benson? Aye, sir.
本森 是 长官
Give Mr. Fisher the first bearing
告诉费雪 你最初测到的
you had on that flattop.
那航母的方位
295, sir.
方位 295 长官
What's that for?
那是什么
Morphine, sir.
吗啡 长官
The shot would help you, sir.
打一针会对你有帮助 长官
It wouldn't help my shooting.
但对我的(鱼雷)发射没有帮助
Are you making a sound attack?
你要靠辨别声音来发动攻击吗
That's right.
没错
You know the chances of getting a hit
你知道 利用声音获得攻击机会
with sound are about 1 in 8?
最后成功的几率只有1/8吗
Not very good odds, are they?
几率不是很理想 对吗？
You want to quit? Uh-uh.
你想要退出吗 嗯
Just checking your plans, in case you pass out.
不 我只是再确认一下你的计划 以防你突然晕倒
I'm getting some strange sounds, captain.
长官 我听到一些奇怪的声音
What do you make of it?
你认为是什么
I don't know.
我不知道
Pretty faint yet.
还很微弱
Bearing?
方位
295.
Come to course 295.
调整航向至295
All ahead 1/3.
全速1/3
That's an anchor chain.
那是拉起锚链的声音
Of course it is.
当然是
Shinaru.
“士那若”号
Sure, she's getting underway.
对 它准备起锚出航了
She's trying to bail out of there
他正试图赶快逃离
before she gets caught.
免得被困住
At 295 and holding.
航向维持在 295
Very well.
很好
Target still stationary, sir.
长官 目标仍静止不动
1,800 yards.
距离1800码
Battle stations torpedo, make ready all bow tubes.
进入战斗岗位 所有鱼雷发射管准备
Can you shoot?
你能发射吗
I can.
我可以
Take the sound.
你负责听声音
Destroyer coming up fast.
有驱逐舰正快速驶来
Right in the groove again.
又要故伎重施
Dive and lose the shot or stay here
下潜就会失去发射机会
and take the beating.
留在原地就会遭到攻击
Maybe lose the boat.
有可能会损失这船
What would you do, Mr. Sloan?
你会怎么做 斯隆先生
Your choice.
你来决定
I came here to learn, remember?
我是来学习的 记得吗
That's why I'm asking you.
所以我才问你
What would you do?
你会怎么做
I'd stay up and shoot.
我会留下来攻击
That's what we're here for.
这是我们来这儿的目的
Group's ready, sir.
全都准备好了 长官
We'll fire 6 at 1,000.
我们在距离一千码时发射六枚
We can fire anytime now, sir.
我们可以随时发射 长官
Every second improves the shot.
每多过一秒都会使成功率增加
You can't, Arch.
你下令吧 阿奇
She's yours, skipper.
它是你的 船长
Ours.
(不) 我们的
You do it.
你来做
Go ahead and shoot, Arch.
去发射吧 阿奇
Go ahead.
快去
All away, captain.
全部发射 长官
Running through the target so far?
到目前为止 直奔目标而去
I hope.
希望如此
What if I missed?
要是我没打中怎么办
That'll be two of us.
那算我们俩都没打中
We aren't gonna miss the shellacking.
海面上的攻击我们是躲不过去了
They're unloading the rack on us.
他们集中所有火力来对付我们
How long to target, Foley?
还要多久击中目标 福利
6 seconds to go, sir.
六秒 长官
(screaming)
(尖叫)
(explosions)
(爆炸)
(indistinct chatter)
(模糊的颤音)
Move it! Move it!
快点 快点
(indistinct chatter)
(模糊的颤音)快到指挥舱去
All right! Get up!
好吧 上去
Hurry! Up!
快点上去
Can't close it, Barney!
关不上了 巴尼
Put 50 pounds of pressure in there!
给这里再加压50磅
Aye, sir!
是 长官
Benson?
本森
Forward battery rooms are all right,
电瓶室暂时没问题
we still got lights.
因为还有光线
Now, Goldy? Sir.
戈尔迪 长官
SOSBluefinto stand by, we're abandoning ship.
紧急呼叫蓝鳍金枪鱼号 做好准备 我们准备弃船
I can't get anything, sir.
我听不到任何声音 长官
(explosion)
(爆炸)
All, I can--
只有...
Wait!
等一下
Listen, torpedoes!
有鱼雷的声音
She's fired at that destroyer, sir!
它正在攻击驱逐舰 长官
Keep calling theBluefin. Keep calling!
继续呼叫蓝鳍金枪鱼号 继续呼叫
What's the count, Mr. Buckeye?
情况怎么样 巴凯
Twenty here, sir, and the lot should be
我们这里有20个人 长官
safe in the forward torpedo room.
眼下只有艇首鱼雷舱比较安全
Keep calling.
继续呼叫
I'm broadcasting, sir.
我正在发报 长官
Captain, I have an SOS fromGreyfish.
船长 角鲨号在呼救
Where are they?
他们在哪儿
Right here, sir.
就在这里 长官
We must be directly over them.
我们应该是在他们的正上方
All stop!
停车
Now we can call.
回应呼救
Aye aye, sir.
是 长官
I got them.
我联络上了
I got them, captain, I got them!
我联络上了 长官 我联络上他们了
Tell them to stand by. We'll start escape.
叫他们做好准备 我们要开始弃船
Break out the battle lanterns.
准备好应急潜水灯
(coughing)
(咳嗽)
Fisher, break out the Momsen lungs.
费雪 分发应急潜水设备
Aye, sir.
是 长官
Foley, Benson, break out the ascending line,
福利 本森 准备紧急爬升绳
we're going up.
我们要上去
Aye, sir. Aye, sir.
是 长官 是 长官
Captain! Captain!
船长 船长
It's theBluefin,sir.
是蓝鳍金枪鱼号 长官
Now let's go.
好 我们走
Now let's move.
准备行动
Aye! Come on!
是 走吧
Arch. See if you can get the torpedo room.
阿奇 看能否跟鱼雷舱联系上
Aye, sir.
是 长官
Fisher, charge the Momsens with oxygen.
费雪 更换一下应急氧气
Aye aye, sir.
是 长官
Let's move in.
我们走吧
They have access, sir.
他们有回应 长官
Tell them to escape. Aye, sir.
告诉他们准备离船 是 长官
Ever felt anything this cold?
有感觉过这么冷吗
Lord, yes!
上帝啊 有
Brighton in August.
八月天里 在布莱顿海边
Open the front valve.
打开顶舱阀门
That's it.
都好了吗
That's it, sir.
都好了 长官
All right, now listen to me.
好了 现在听我说
Go up steady and take it easy.
稳稳的上去 慢慢来别紧张
Breathe in and out real slow
呼吸都要非常缓慢
so you don't hurt your lungs.
这样你的肺才不会受伤
You hear me back there?
后面的都听见了吗
Yes, sir. Aye, sir.
是 长官 是 长官
Everybody set?
大家都准备好了吗
Yes, sir. Aye, sir.
是 长官 是 长官
Come on, let's go.
来吧 我们走
This is a standard drill.
就当是次标准演习
And I want to see every one of your ugly faces up there.
我要到那边看到 你们每张丑脸
Waiting for us.
都在等着我们
Part the hatch.
打开舱门
(alarm blaring)
(警报响起)
Hurry it up!
快点上来
The fog is lifting!
雾开始散了
(siren wailing)
(警笛嚎叫)
(indistinct chatter)
(模糊的颤音)
Coffee, captain?
咖啡 船长
Coffee to the conning tower.
给指挥舱来点儿咖啡
Steady on 025, sir.
保持航向 025 长官
Very well.
很好
Thanks, Benny.
谢谢 巴尼
Thanks a lot.
非常感谢
Here you are, Barney.
给你 巴尼
Thanks a lot.
非常感谢
How about the men?
那些船员呢
Chief Hallert says six men unreported
哈勒船长说 有六个在艇尾
from the aft torpedo room.
鱼雷舱 还未报告
Who are they?
他们是那几个
Philips, Owens, and Hughes,
菲利浦 欧文 和休斯
Abrahams, Sherman, and Howard.
亚伯拉罕 舍曼 和霍华德
Look, Barney, two of you better get below,
我说巴尼 你们两个最好到下面去
get some rest. He's right, Barney.
休息一会儿 他说得对 巴尼
Let's go down and get that arm fixed.
我们下去把你的手臂重新固定一下
No, no, wait a minute.
不 不 等一下
Did you get any confirmation?
你有没有确认
From theShinaru?
你是说“士那若”
We couldn't see anything up there.
那边我们什么也看不见
Solid fog.
雾太浓了
Well, look again for me, will you?
你再帮我查一下 好吗
Please.
拜托
All right.
好吧
We heard a couple of hits we thought,
我们好像听见有两枚打中了
but we didn't know with that beating you were taking.
但是你们也受到了重创 所以我们不能确定
Barney.
巴尼
Barney, look at that.
巴尼 你来看看
Pass the word to the rest of my crew, will you?
把这个消息传给我的其他船员 好吗
Pipe this through the ship.
派普 全船通报
Aye, sir.
是 长官
Captain to the crew of theGreyfish.
这是船长致 角鲨号全体船员
Here's a periscope  observation.
通过潜望镜观察到如下情况
Bearing 285,  range 4,000 yards.
在方位285 距离4000码处
The flattop  Shinaruis sinking.
“士那若”号航空母舰正在下沉
She is listing about 30 degrees to the port.
它向左倾斜30度
And she is going down by the bow very fast.
由船头开始 正在急速下沉
She's down by the bow now.
船首已经沉没
Gears rolling off of her decks.
甲板上的装备正在四散脱落
She's slipping, fast.
它下沉得非常快
There she goes.
它完了
Scratch one flattop.
这艘航母被彻底击沉
It's confirmed sinking.
已确认沉没
Well done,Greyfish.
干得漂亮 角鲨号
Down scope.
降下潜望镜
All ahead full, let's get out of here.
全速前进 我们快离开这儿
All ahead full, sir.
全速前进 长官